Finding Aid for Wilber M. Brucker Papers 1877-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Secretary of the Army
  - Audio-tapes of Brucker speeches, November 1954-November 1960; 250 audiotapes 7-inch; reel-to-reel tapes; 2 audiotapes 10-inch; reel-to-reel tapes
    - American Society of Civil Engineers, Buffalo, June 5, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tapes 115, 116)
    - This is Your Life (William Neithercut), June 8, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 117)
    - Fort Myer Review for Army Veteran Members of Congress, June 9, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 118)
    - Presentation of DSM-General Heston, June 10, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 119)
    - Swearing-in of General McNamara, QMG, June 12, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 120)
    - Army War College Graduation, Carlisle, June 20, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tapes 121-123)
    - Rose Garden Flag Presentation, July 10, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 124)
    - June 13, 1956, July 10, 1957 Army Flag Presentation-Capitol & White House Rose Garden (Box 32)
      (Tape 125)
    - Civilian Awards Ceremony, July 10, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tapes 126-127)
    - Farewell for Col. Weyand and Maj. Ivan, July 12, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 128)
    - July 13, 1957. Rainbow Reunion, Fort Meade, Maryland (Box 32)
      (Tape 129)
    - Frankfurt presentation of Army flag to General Hodes (also includes press conference, August 5, 1957, August 2, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tapes 130, 131)
    - Press Conference, V Corps, Frankfurt, Germany, August 5, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tapes 132, 133)
    - Award to Admiral Strauss, August 14, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 134)
    - Army Flag Presentation to Army Secretariat and General Lemnitzer, August 14, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 135)
    - Presentation of Army Flag to General Wyman, August 15, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 136)
    - Promotion S.L.A. Marshall, August 16, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 137)
    - Presentation of Amy Flag to 6th Army, August 21, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 138)
    - Promotion-Frank McCarthy, August 23, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 139)
    - Press Conference-3rd Army, August 28, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 140)
    - Presentation of Army Flag to Gen. Bradley, October 16, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 141)
    - Yorktown Monument Dedication, circa October 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tapes 142, 143)
    - Presentation of Army Flag to Gen. MacArthur, November 6, 1957 (Box 32)
      (Tape 144)
    - Bridge Dedication, Veteran Day Luncheon and Wilson Testimonial-Detroit., November 11, 1957 (Box 33)
      (Tape 145)
    - Missile Master Presentation-Fort Meade, December 5, 1957 (Box 33)
      (Tape 146)
    - Presentation DCSM to Dr. Ellis Johnson, January 16, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 147)
    - Explorer Launching, January 31, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tapes 174-180)
    - Interview with Senator Potter, 1958 February 10; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 5 inch
      - [Part 1], [85874-SR-148-1]; mp3 file; (Interview with Senator Potter in the Capitol Building about defense spending in Michigan, defense contracts in the state, and Jupiter missile production. February 10, 1958. Included sheet)
    - Union League Club, New York City, April 10, 1958; 7 in. and 10 in. tapes (Box 33)
      (Tapes 149, 150)
    - News Conference, Phoenix, Arizona, April 15, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 151)
    - Chamber of Commerce, San Antonio, Texas, April 16, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tapes 152, 153)
    - Press Conference, San Antonio, Texas, April 16, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 154)
    - Fort Myer (S/A), May 2, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 155)
    - Visit to Raytheon Manufacturing Co., May 17, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 156)
    - Opening of Army Museum-Smithsonian, June 14, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 157)
    - Review Honoring Red Cross, June 15, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 158)
    - Mackinac Bridge Dedication, 1958 June 28; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [85874-SR-159-1]; mp3 file; (Mr. Brucker gives a speech at the Mackinac Bridge Dedication event.)
    - Project Ammo, June 20, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tapes 160, 161)
    - Kiwanis Convention, June 30, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tapes 162, 163)
    - S/A News Conference Chicago, Ill., June 30, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 164)
    - Press Conference Rainbow Convention, July 14, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tapes 165, 166)
    - Far East-Korea, August 29, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 167 and 167-a)
    - Press Conference, Taiwan, September 1, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 168)
    - Press Conference, Chicago, October 18, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tapes 169, 170)
    - Chicago Tribune Awards, October 18, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tape 171)
    - Assn. U.S. Army Sheraton Park, October 22, 1958 (Box 33)
      (Tapes 172, 173)
    - Explorer Launching, 1958 January 31; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [85874-SR-174-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 1; Radio broadcast from the Explorer 1 launch and the ballistic missiles used to launch it from WTOP.)
    - Explorer Launching, 1958 January 31; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [85874-SR-175-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 2; Radio broadcast from the Explorer 1 launch and the ballistic missiles used to launch it from WTOP.)
    - Explorer Launching, 1958 January 31; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [85874-SR-176-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 3; Radio broadcast from the Explorer 1 launch and the ballistic missiles used to launch it from WTOP.)
    - Explorer Launching, 1958 January 31; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [85874-SR-177-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 4; Radio broadcast from the Explorer 1 launch and the ballistic missiles used to launch it from WTOP.)
    - Explorer Launching, 1958 January 31; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [85874-SR-178-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 5; Radio broadcast from the Explorer 1 launch and the ballistic missiles used to launch it from WTOP.)
    - Explorer Launching, 1958 January 31; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [85874-SR-179-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 6; Radio broadcast from the Explorer 1 launch and the ballistic missiles used to launch it from WTOP.)
    - Explorer Launching, 1958 January 31; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [85874-SR-180-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 7; Radio broadcast from the Explorer 1 launch and the ballistic missiles used to launch it from WTOP.)
    - Presentation of Distinguished Service Medal to General Holle, October 27, 1958 (Box 34)
      (Tape 181)
    - Veterans Day-Welch, West Virginia., November 11, 1958 (Box 34)
      (Tape 182)
    - Association of National Advertisers, November 12, 1958 (Box 34)
      (Tape 183)
    - Silver Anniversary, Inland Empire Waterways Association, December 13, 1958 (Box 34)
      (Tapes 184, 185)
    - Press Conference, Fort Lewis, Washington, December 13, 1958 (Box 34)
      (Tape 186)
    - Chamber of Commerce, Anchorage, AK, December 15, 1958 (Box 34)
      (Tapes 187-190)
    - Legion of Merit to Duke of Sparta, February 27, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 191)
    - ROTC Conference, March 12, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 192 & 192-a)
    - Frank Higgins Ceremony, March 16, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 193)
    - Press Conference, Berlin, April 16, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 194)
    - S/A Speech, Berlin, April 17, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 195)
    - AUSA Luncheon-Fort Ord., May 1, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 196)
    - Press Conference, Cincinnati, May 12, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 197)
    - National Association of Broadcasters, July 19, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tapes 198, 199)
    - Colonel Dalrymple farewell, July 30, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 200)
    - Martha Rountree Interview, August 4, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 201)
    - Association of U.S. Army Meeting, August 5, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tapes 202-204)
    - Today Show-Secretary Brucker, August 5, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 205)
    - Winona Lake Bible Conference, September 7, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tapes 206, 207)
    - Interview (T.V.) Dr. Schwarzwalder, September 9, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 208)
    - Interview with Honorable Silvio Conte, September 12, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 209)
    - 99th Anniversary John J. Pershing, September 13, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 210)
    - 175th Anniversary, 3rd Infantry, September 20, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tape 211)
    - Civilian Aide Conference, September 23, 1959 (Box 34)
      (Tapes 212, 213)
    - Press Conference Fort Bragg, North Carolina, September 23, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tape 214)
    - Review American Gold Star Mothers, September 27, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tape 215)
    - Dr. York briefing, October 5, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tape 216)
    - National Day of Prayer-Pentagon, October 7, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tapes 217, 218)
    - Press Conference, Aberdeen Proving Grounds, October 8, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tape 219)
    - One Army Luncheon Talk, October 21, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tape 220)
    - Dr. Glennan Talk, October 22, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tape 221)
    - College News Conference, November 8, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tape 222)
    - DCSM Presentation to Mr. T. Voorhees, November 18, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tape 223)
    - Annual World Wide Info. Officers' Conference, December 1, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tape 224)
    - Unity of Action, December 8, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tapes 225, 226)
    - Surgeon General's Meeting Walter Reed, December 17, 1959 (Box 35)
      (Tapes 227, 228)
    - Rees Award presentation, June 21, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tape 229)
    - Birthday celebration, June 23, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tape 230)
    - Review honoring WMB's Fifth Anniversary as S/A, July 21, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tapes 231-234)
    - Col. Guthrie departure, August 5, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tape 2353)
    - Gen. Hendrick's plaque for ABMA, August 19, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tapes 236, 237)
    - Gen. Yates Legion of Merit Award, August 24, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tape 238)
    - American Bar Association Panel, August 31, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tapes 239-242)
    - September 13, 1960 Copy of Speech of John J, Pershing, September 12, 1924 used during Centennial Celebration (Box 35)
      (Tape 243)
    - National Press Club, Pershing Round Table Discussion, September 26, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tape 244)
    - Scientific Advisory Panel Banquet, Fort Knox, Kentucky, October 26, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tape 245)
    - Civilian Service Award to Colonel James Totten, Sr., October 27, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tape 246)
    - Dedication of Whitehall Memorial U.S. Army Reserve Center, Columbus, Ohio, October 29, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tape 247)
    - Presentation of Legion of Merit to Lt. Col. Chester E. Whiting, October 31, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tape 248)
    - Consolidated Mess, Fort Leslie J. McNair, November 24, 1960 (Box 35)
      (Tape 249)
    - Interview in Greece re. armed forces, Undated (Box 35)
      (Tape 250)
    - American Bar Association Panel (Holme Malone, Seymour, Brucker), Undated; 10 in. sound tape (Box 35)
      (Tapes 251, 252)
  - Itineraries and brochures of Tours as Secretary of the Army
    - 1955-1960 (Box 36)
    - 1955-1960 (Box 37)
      (continued)
    - 1955-1960 (Box 38)
- Newspaper clippings, 1916-1968
  Newspaper clippings date from 1916 to 1968 and are a good source for information about Brucker as Republican politician and governor in the 1930s and his work with legislative reapportionment in the 1960s.
  - Undated, 3 folders (Box 39)
  - 1916-1927 (Box 39)
  - 1928-1929 (Box 39)
  - 1930, 4 folders (Box 39)
  - 1931, 16 folders (Box 39)
  - 1932, 13 folders (Box 39)
  - 1932, 9 folders (Box 40)
  - 1933, 2 folders (Box 40)
  - 1934, 3 folders (Box 40)
  - 1936, 7 folders (Box 40)
  - 1937 (Box 40)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 40)
  - Concerning St. Lawrence Seaway, 1928-1933 (Box 40)
  - Concerning St. Lawrence Seaway, 1934-1938 (Box 40)
  - 1940, 2 folders (Box 40)
  - 1941-1944 (Box 40)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 40)
  - 1947 (Box 40)
  - Concerning one man grand jury, 1947-1948 (Box 40)
  - Concerning one man grand jury, 1949 (Box 40)
  - 1948, 2 folders (Box 40)
  - Concerning Brucker vs. Eugene Black Slander case, 1948-1950 (Box 41)
    - 1948 (Box 41)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 41)
  - Concerning Michigan Auto Dealers Association vs. Eugene Black, 1948-1959 (Box 41)
  - 1949 (Box 41)
  - 1950 (Box 41)
  - 1951 (Box 41)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 41)
  - 1954 (Box 41)
  - 1955 (Box 41)
  - 1956 (Box 41)
  - 1957 (Box 41)
  - 1958, 2 folders (Box 41)
  - 1959 (Box 41)
  - 1960 (Box 41)
  - 1961 (Box 41)
  - 1962 (Box 41)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 41)
  - Concerning Reapportionment, 1963-1966
    - 1963 (Box 41)
    - 1964, 5 folders (Box 41)
    - 1965, 2 folders (Box 41)
    - 1966 (Box 41)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 41)
  - Concerning death of Wilber Brucker, 1968 (Box 41)
- Personal: Albums, scrapbooks, etc
  Personal: Albums, Scrapbooks, etc. contains Brucker's extensive collection of scrapbooks and photograph albums. The scrapbooks represent a narrative in newspaper clippings of Brucker's career in state government during the first years of the Depression, roughly 1929 to 1936. The photograph albums depict the same period in time, and include pictures of the governor's vigorous campaign activities, photographs of him with President Herbert Hoover, and personal shots of Brucker with his family. Together, there are eleven volumes of scrapbooks and six photograph albums. Included in this personal series is Brucker's collection of letters written by Michigan governors, including John J. Bagley, Josiah Begole, Lewis Cass, Charles M. Croswell, Alpheus Felch, Woodbridge N. Ferris, Epaphroditus Ransom, and Moses Wisner.
  - Photograph Albums and Scrapbooks, 1898-1940; 3 volumes (Box 42)
    - 1898-1932 (Box 42)
    - 1932-1936 (Box 42)
    - 1936-1940 (Box 42)
  - Photograph Albums, 1931; 2 volumes (Box 42)
  - Scrapbook, 1948 (Box 42)
  - Photograph Album, 1953 (Box 42)
  - Scrapbooks
    - January 1929-April 1930 (Box 43)
    - April 1930-July 1930 (Box 43)
    - July 1930-September 1930 (Box 43)
    - September 1930-November 1930 (Box 43)
    - November 1930-May 1931 (Box 43)
    - May 1931-August 1931 (Box 43)
    - August 1931-December 1932 (Box 43)
    - January 1933-October 1936 (Box 43)
  - Family Scrapbooks and Photograph Albums, 5 volumes (Box 44)
  - Saginaw High-School Yearbook
    - 1900 (Box 45)
    - 1901 (Box 45)
    - 1904 (Box 45)
    - 1906 (Box 45)
    - 1907 (Box 45)
    - 1911 (Box 45)
    - 1912 (Box 45)
    - 1913 (Box 45)
  - Kiwanis Krier, 1948 weekly publication of Kiwanis Club No. 1, Detroit, 1948 (Box 45)
    (Brucker was president for 1948)
  - Secretary of the Army, 1955-1960; Problems and Accomplishments by Wilber M. Brucker, Sr. and Wilber M. Brucker, Jr., 2 volumes (Box 45)
  - "Original letters of Governors of Michigan" (Box 45)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials consist of loose photographs filed by subject, photograph albums and motion pictures from the period when he was secretary of the army.
  - Photographs
    - Brucker, Ferdinand and Roberta (parents) (Box 46)
    - Brucker, Wilber M., early photos (Box 46)
    - Brucker, Wilber M., portraits, 2 folders (Box 46)
    - Brucker, Mrs. Wilber (Clara Hantel), and father Reverend Emil Hantel (Box 46)
    - Brucker, Mr. and Mrs. Wilber M. and son Wilber, Jr (Box 46)
    - Air Force inspection, 1954 (Box 46)
    - American Legion Convention, Detroit, 1931 (Box 46)
    - Armed Forces Management Association Conference, 1965; undated (Box 46)
    - Associates and friends: General Bruce C. Clarke and Colonel George M. Seignions, 1962 (Box 46)
    - Associates and friends: A-M (Box 46)
    - Associates and friends: N-Z (Box 46)
    - Association of the U.S. Army (AUSA) (Box 46)
    - Award received, including those from the Freedom Foundation, Valley Forge 1959 AUSA, 1962 L.L.D. from the University of Michigan, 1955 (Box 46)
    - Early career (Box 46)
    - Entertainment (Box 46)
    - Family, family friends (early pictures) (Box 46)
    - Farewell Ceremonies, Ft. Meyer, VA, January 19, 1961 (Box 46)
    - Farewell Ceremonies, Pentagon, January 20, 1961 (Box 46)
    - Farewell visit to Ft. Carson and Colorado Springs, CO (Box 46)
    - Funeral of Mrs. Roberta Brucker (mother of William M. Brucker), 1939 (Box 46)
    - Gamble, Burt, trial, Saginaw, 1924 (Box 46)
    - Governors' Conference, 1931 (Box 46)
    - Gubernatorial activities (Box 46)
    - Hoover, Herbert, photos with William M. Brucker (Box 46)
    - Knights Templar. Grand Commandery.
      - Cleveland Triennial, August 1961 (Box 46)
      - Detroit (Box 46)
      - Indiana, May 1965 (Box 46)
      - Los Angeles (Box 46)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 46)
      - Odessa, TX, May 1965 (Box 46)
      - Washington, D.C., Easter Sunrise Service, 1960 (Box 46)
      - Washington, D.C., Grand Encampment Officers (Box 46)
    - Law School. Class of 1916 and faculty (Box 46)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 46)
    - Murphy, Frank. Photos with William M. Brucker at American Legion Convention, Detroit, 1931 (Box 46)
    - Otto, Herbert A. Testimonial Dinner given by Robert Brucker, April 9, 1951 (Box 46)
    - Poe Lock, Sault Ste. Marie, Dedication, June 26, 1969 (Box 46)
    - Public appearances. Miscellaneous, circa 1930-1968 (Box 46)
    - Public appearances re: Army, 1955-1960 (Box 46)
    - Public appearances re: Army, 1961-1965 (Box 46)
      (see also Zussman Army Reserve Center folder)
    - R.O.T.C. National Convention, June 1956 (Box 46)
    - Rainbow Division (U.S. Army, 166th Infantry, A.E.F., 42nd Division, W.W.I) (Box 46)
    - Saginaw Airport (dedication of portrait) (Box 46)
    - Saginaw. Neighborhood House (Box 46)
    - Secretary's Conference, Quantico, 1957 (Box 46)
    - State Fair Board, 1931 (Box 46)
    - Taiwan, Korea trips (Box 46)
    - U.S. Army equipment and maneuvers (Box 46)
    - World War I (Mexican Border campaign) (Box 46)
    - Zussman Army Reserve Center dedication, Bay City, MI (Box 46)
      (see also Public Appearances re: Army, 1961-1965 folder)
    - Clara Brucker
      - Wilber Brucker funeral, October 1968 (Box 46)
      - Mock Republican National Convention, 1952 (Box 46)
      - School of Government speakers and officials (Box 46)
      - Miscellaneous (include family photos) (Box 46)
  - Photograph Albums
    - Family members (early pictures) (Box 47)
    - European trip (includes Turkey), 1959 (Box 47)
    - Far Eastern trip, 1959-1960 (Box 47)
      folder 1
    - Far Eastern trip, 1959-1960 (Box 48)
      folder 2
    - January 20, 1960-May 31, 1960 (Box 48)
  - Framed and oversized
    - Framed Photographs and Memorabilia (Box 49)
      (formerly on exhibit in the Wilber Brucker Room)
    - Oversized photographs (Box 50)
      (see also oversized folder UAl)
  - Films
    (all 16 mm., black & white, sound, except where noted)
    - University of Michigan-Army football game (Box 51)
      (color, silent, ca. 5 min.; no. 99)
    - Meet the Press, September 4, 1955 (Box 51)
      (ca. 30 min.; no. 102)
    - Association of the U.S. Army meeting, October 26, 1956 (Box 51)
      (ca. 30 min.; no. 141)
    - Presenting army flag to President Eisenhower, July 10, 1957 (Box 51)
      (ca. 5 min.; no. 96)
    - German interview, August 1957 (Box 51)
      (silent with separate magnetic sound track, ca. 5 min.; unnumbered)
    - Association of the U.S. Army meeting, October 30, 1957 (Box 51)
      (ca. 30 min.; no. 157)
    - Face the Nation, November 24, 1957; 2 reels (Box 52)
      (ca. 30 min.; nos. 132 and 103)
    - College News Conference, March 17, 1958 (Box 52)
      (ca. 30 min.; no. 140)
    - Fourth anniversary as Secretary of the Army, July 21, 1959 (Box 52)
      (silent, ca. 10 min.; no. 98)
    - Visiting Korea, January 1960 (Box 52)
      (ca. 5 min.; no. 97)
    - At unidentified military installation, undated (Box 52)
      (silent, ca. 2 min.; no. 133)